"West Meditation Temple"
"Tong Qianjin, Shaolin disciple"
"Leopard Kid, Wudang Clan"
小孩，让开点
Move aside, kid!
"Nian Ruiqing, Shaolin disciple"
"Tiger Kid, Wudang Clan"
"Li Jinlun, Shaolin disciple"
"Fan Tiancong, Wudang Clan"
"Monk Sande, Shaolin disciple"
"Zou Feng, Wudang Clan"
"Hong Xiguan, Shaolin disciple"
"Priest White Brows, Wudang Clan"
洪举官你快走，去找至善师父
Hong Xiguan, run! Go find our master Zhishan.
快走啊
Run!
"Hu Weigan, Shaolin disciple"
"Gao Jinzhong, the best student of White Brows"
"Xiang Yuan Wine Shop"
看打
Watch it!
别打
Stop!
让开
Move over!
你看看日头已经老高了
It's already mid-day,
还不好好做生意
why aren't you working?
你们在干什么？
What are you doing?
除了吃饭你还会做什么？
What do you know except eating?
老板，我半夜起身推磨做豆腐
Boss, I woke up almost at midnight to make tofu,
到现在一夜都没停过
and I didn't get a break.
我请你做伙计就是不准你停
That's the point of hiring you;
做…不停的做
Working non-stop.
我不做了，你做吧
I quit. You can do it.
阿金
Jin.
请
Please.
让开，豆腐来了
Move over, the tofu.
阿金…我…
Jin... l...
擦擦汗总可以吧
Guess I could at least wipe off the sweat.
黄老板，伙计抹抹汗不算偷懒吧
Boss Huang, I don't think he's idling,
对不对？
agree?
黄老板小心点
Careful, Boss Huang.
要是捧不住
If you can't hold it,
这十来架豆腐就血本无归了
then it will be a disaster.
阿金，快来帮个忙
Jin, come help!
来了…
Coming...
老板，您有什么吩咐？
Yes, boss?
黄老板，别怪阿金不做生意
Boss Huang, don't blame Jin that he's not working.
我就是来买豆腐的
I'm here to buy some tofu.
杨大宝，你还想不想干？
Yang Dabao, you want me to fire you?
买点豆腐去了那么久
You took quite a while to buy tofu!
像你这样我别做生意了
I've got a restaurant to run here.
是，老板，我这不回来了吗
Yes, boss. Well, I'm back now.
快摆好桌子
Set the tables.
老板，你得让开点
Excuse me, boss.
我总得把豆腐拿到厨房里去
I need to bring these to the kitchen.
快点…手脚俐落点
Hurry up!
老板，请坐…两位吃点什么？
This way please. What would you like to eat?
伙计，来两碗牛肉面
Two bowls of beef noodles.
好
Right away.
牛肉面两碗
Two bowls of beef noodles.
两位坐，吃点什么？
Welcome. What would you like?
蒸牛肉、煮水蛋，半斤白干，快点
Steamed beef, steamed egg and some wine. Hurry!
客倌，坐
Please have a seat.
两位
Welcome.
切鸡一盘
A dish of chicken.
好
Okay
喂，大爷有事，快点
Hey! I'm in a rush here! Hurry up!
是…听见没有？
Yes... can't you hear?
这两位爷儿们要先上
Bring the dishes to them first.
好，我知道了
Got it.
来了，快点快点
Coming. Hurry!
客倌，对不起
Sorry, sir.
大人有大量，我可不是故意的
I was careless.
鼻子
The nose.
起来起来，对不起
Get up. Sorry.
老板，这个鸡腿上有个苍蝇
Boss, there's a fly on this chicken leg,
要不要把它给扔掉？
should I throw it away?
啊？扔了？
Throw it away?
把这个苍蝇弄掉照样给他们吃
Get rid of the fly, and give it to them.
喂，这鸡腿怎么这样？
Hey, what's wrong with this?
请放心，这个鸡腿上本来有个苍蝇
Don't worry. There's a fly here,
老板吩咐我把它给弄掉
the boss told me to get rid of it.
不要紧的，尽管吃好了
Don't worry, eat up.
老板，这怎么吃啊？
How can I eat it?
我们这儿东西是绝对干净
Our food is very clean here.
不要听他胡说八道，你这小子
Don't listen to him.
两位
Gentlemen.
最要紧的是上好门板，收拾好铺子
Be sure to lock the shop up.
洗干净所有的东西
Clean up everything.
泡好明天要磨的豆子
Soak the beans for tomorrow.
早点起来推磨
Wake up early to grind the beans.
干什么？你要砸铺子？
What now? Are you trying to wreck the shop?
推好了磨马上煮豆汁
When you're done, start to boil the juice.
煮好了豆汁
When you've boiled the juice,
一边做豆腐一边做豆腐干
make some tofu and dried tofu.
一边炸豆腐，你可别偷懒
And you can deep-fry some, don't try to slack off.
我要是知道你偷懒就得扣工钱
If I find out, I'll deduct it from your pay.
砸烂了东西也得扣工钱
If you break anything, that's coming off your pay too.
开门晚了我还是得扣工钱
And if you open the shop late, I'll deduct your pay.
是
Yes.
奇怪，怎么每天临走都得摔一跤
It's strange! Why do I trip everyday?
杨大宝
Yang Dabao.
你在上边干什么？
What are you doing up there?
我来看
Let me see what your
看你们黑虎门练什么叫化子功夫
Black Tiger Clan's martial arts style is all about
你懂什么，这就叫点指神仙钵
What do you know? This is the fairy's bowl.
我说这是叫化子钵
I think it's more like a beggar's bowl.
来，只要你能够抢到这个叫化子钵
Alright. If you can snatch this beggar's bowl,
就有好东西吃
you're in for a yummy treat.
戴上
Wear it.
叫化子钵在我这儿了
I've got it!
快拿东西来吃
Yummy food!
好
Very well.
你信不信如果我不想让你吃
Do you believe that with this pair of chopsticks
就凭我这双筷子
I can stop you from eating?
说什么你也进不了口
You don't have a chance to eat anything.
我跟我爹学武的时候
When I was learning martial arts from my dad,
就是躲不开他这双筷子
that's what he did.
整整吃了大半年的白饭
For over half a year, I ate plain rice.
我们家传黑虎门的武功
The main feature of the martial arts of my family,
最大的特点就是
the Black Tiger Clan is that,
身边不论有什么东西
we can pick up anything handy beside us,
都可以拿来做武器
and use it as a weapon.
在吃饭的时候…
While we're eating...
吃大半年的白饭滋味可不好捱
Ain't very nice to eat plain rice for over six months.
可不是嘛
Definitely not.
不过等我爹制不住我的时候…
But when my dad couldn't stop me...
你明白了？
Do you get it?
我先吞下去有空再慢慢的嚼
Swallow first, then chew later.
黑虎门功夫
For the Black Tiger Clan's martial arts,
随手可拿到的东西不论大小
we can pick up anything handy beside us,
都可以做兵器
and use it as a weapon.
真不简单
That's really something.
你也别客气了
Don't be modest.
你练的螳螂也是上乘功夫
The Mantis Style you're learning is very difficult too.
没有听你提起过你的师傅是谁
I've never heard about your master.
连我也不知道是谁
I don't know who he is.
哪有这种事？
How can that be?
我遇到我师傅是在三年前
I met my master three years ago.
我还在乡下
I was still in my hometown then
小子，一人叫一声爷爷就放过你
Kid, c'mon address me as "grandpa" and I'll let you go.
龟孙子
Bastard!
小子，你叫不叫
Come on, kid!
龟孙子
Bastard!
爷爷饶命…爷爷
Spare us, "grandpa"!
拜见师傅…
Master.
再试试这个
Try this.
过了两年，师傅不告而别
My master left after two years.
我连他老人家的姓名都不知道
I didn't even know his name.
这才是世外高人
That's a true master.
你我都有一身的功夫
Both of us have skills,
在这个街市上混
I don't know how long
不知道哪天才有出人头地的日子
we must wait to become something in this field
做一番英雄事业
that we can do something great!
如果有这一天我拼了这条命都肯
I'd risk my life for that day!
好
Great!
我们两个人都想做英雄人物
We both want to be heroes,
可是就是不知道
we just don't know
要等到哪一天才能够做得到
when that will happen.
真气人
I can't wait.
早晚有这么一天的
It will happen one of these days.
好家伙，说打就打
Alright! A fight!
打和
Get even!
我晕了
I'm going to faint.
还说做英雄好汉
And you said you want to be a hero,
连坛酒都舍不得
you can't let go of this wine.
不是我舍不得，是老板舍不得
It's not me, it's my boss.
在没有做英雄之前还得吃饭
I still need ajob before I become a hero.
对不对？
Right?
快点睡觉吧
Go to sleep.
半夜里还得起来推磨
You need to get up to work in the middle of the night.
"Qingyun Temple"
啊，洪举官
Hong Xiguan.
"Master Zhishan, Shaolin Monastery"
洪师兄
Brother Hong.
"Fang Shiyu, Shaolin disciple"
"Fang Meiyu"
"Fang Xiaoyu"
扶他起来
Help him up.
别动他，扶他坐好
Don't move him, help him to sit up.
至善师父
Master Zhishan.
举官，你内伤沉重
Xiguan, you have serious internal injuries.
这位是喇嘛派的星龙长老
This is Master Xinglong of Lama Clan.
善于治伤，你且别动
He's a healer, don't move.
师父，西禅寺已经被白眉道人
Master, the West Meditation Temple has been torn apart
高进忠和武当派的人给破了
by White Brows Priest, Gao Jinzhong and the others.
三德师兄、童千斤、年瑞卿
Brother Sande, Tong Qianjin, Nian Ruiqing,
李锦纶、胡惠干他们都…
Li Jinlun, Hu Weigan... they're all dead.
七情六欲，澎湃翻腾
Being emotional is the cause of internal injuries.
是内伤之本，吸气
Inhale.
我全明白了
I understand.
他们迟早会到庆云寺来
They will come to Qingyun Temple eventually.
你伤得很重，一时之间难以痊愈
You're badly injured, it will take some time to heal.
我弟子中有个叫周成的开设武馆
My student Zhou Cheng runs a martial arts school.
你可以去找他，由他替你慢慢治伤
You can look for him, and he can take care of you.
白眉、高进忠要是再来
If White Brows and Gao Jinzhong come here,
我正好跟他们拼命
I've to put up a fight with them.
你伤成这样留此无益，还不快走
You can't help in your state. You should leave soon.
韩七如今在红船当小武
Han Qi works as an acrobat with a theatre troupe.
你可跟他联络
You can contact him.
我们西藏喇嘛派不便卷入
Our Tibetan Lama Clan don't want to get involved
中土朝廷和少林之争，告辞了
in the fight between the Court and Shaolin, goodbye.
你等一等，我进去开一张药方给你
Wait. I'll give you a prescription.
是
Yes.
世玉你去拿点衣服银两来给举官
Shiyu, pack some clothes and money for Xiguan.
是
Yes.
我和世玉、美玉、孝玉
I'll stay here temporarily
他们暂时留在此地
with Shiyu, Meiyu and Xiaoyu.
一等走散的同门聚集
After we've gathered the rest of the students,
也会和韩七联络找你
we'll contact Han Qi and yourself.
是，师父
Yes, master.
我可以送你一程
I could walk some distance with you.
告诉你去找周成的地方
I'll tell you how to get to Zhou Cheng.
"Zhou Cheng Martial Arts School"
"Lama Clan"
本派的桩法与普通的梅花桩不同
These are different from the usual setup.
是按北斗七星排列
Ours is based on the Big Dipper constellation.
高低有异，共七七四十九根
Forty nine in total, all different in height.
这些你们都知道了
You all know that.
知道了
Yes.
你们按我平时的传授
Practise hard
好好地用心练习
from what I have taught you.
是
Yes.
好，慢慢练
Good! Continue practising!
日子长了，在七星桩上面
After a certain time, it won't feel
就会像在地面上一样
any different up there from what it's on the ground
朱财怎么还没来？
Where's Zhu Cai?
师傅
Master.
站住
Wait.
你这个时候才来像是练功夫的人吗
You're late. Do you take your lesson seriously?
今天染房里事多
It's very busy at the dye factory today.
我赶着做完了才来，是迟了一点
I rushed here as soon as I could leave.
那你就回染房去吧
Then you should head back.
像你这样练功夫怎么练得成
You can never learn the way you are.
说起来你是我周成的徒弟
I'm ashamed that
给我丢脸
you're my student.
你们看看他想跟我动手
Look! He tries to hit me.
喂，师傅叫你回染房去
Hey! The master sent you back to the dye factory.
你怎么还不走？
What are you doing here still?
我练完七星桩再回去
I'll leave after I've practised.
练七星桩？
Practise on the Big Dipper poles?
好啊，来，我陪你上桩练练
Very well. Come on!
桩上过招容易受伤
It's easy to get injured there.
你是万金之躯我可不敢
I dare not hurt you.
就凭你？
Do you honestly think you can?
上
Go up!
你们看看他多听话
Look how he listens to me!
朱财，你这是干什么？
Zhu Cai, what on earth are you doing?
同门过招，你怎么出手这么重？
How could you be so severe on your classmate?
师傅，他…
Master, he...
你自以为练得不错了，是不是？
You think you've mastered it, don't you?
好，我跟你过几招
Fine, challenge me.
弟子不敢
I dare not to, master.
阿金，我走了
Jin, I'm off.
朱财，站住
Stand still, Zhu Cai.
你们听着，你们替我打
Listen up! Beat him up!
打中一拳，踢中一脚一两银子
I'll pay a tael of silver for every punch and kick!
喂，你怎么不还手？
Hey! Why didn't you fight back?
就算打不过也要拼命啊
You must try your best even if there's no hope to win.
打，打中一拳一两银子
Come on! You'll get paid.
我打中一拳，你欠我一两银子
One punch, you owe me a tael.
我连中五拳，前后六两
Five punches, six taels of silver all together.
你到底有没有钱给？
Can you afford it?
一共是一百三十四两，你给不给？
One hundred and thirty four taels. Pay up.
一百五十
One hundred and fifty.
一百七十八
One hundred and seventy eight.
一百九十，一百九十八
One hundred and ninety, one hundred and ninety eight.
一百九十九
One hundred and ninety nine.
正好两百两
Two hundred!
走啊
Run.
多谢两位，这几位都是我的师兄弟
Thanks, they're all my classmates at the kung fu school
两位请住手吧
Please stop.
这算什么师傅？
What kind of a master is he?
有钱不一定练得好功夫
A rich person won't necessarily learn well.
我看你的功夫就比同门师兄弟强
I think you're better than the rest of them.
我练了七星桩，请多多指教
I've learnt martial arts on the Big Dipper Poles.
七星桩？在哪里？
Big Dipper Poles? Where?
我们来过两招
Let's have some fun.
我没站好
I lost my balance.
你不行，让我来
My turn!
好，在桩上是你行
Very well! You rule on the poles.
到饭店就看我的了
But I'm better at the restaurant.
到了豆腐店就要看我的功夫
And I'm the best in the tofu shop.
"Qingyun Temple."
韩七？
Han Qi?
我才叫洪举官到红船和你联络
I sent Hong Xiguan to contact you!
你怎么来了？
What are you doing here?
至善师父，外面风声很紧
Master Zhishan, it's very dangerous out there.
我来告诉你
I'm here to inform you.
我知道了，你快回去
I know, just head back.
洪举官受了伤，一定要赶快找到他
Hong Xiguan is injured, you must hurry and find him.
我们暂时留在这里
We're staying here temporarily.
直等逃出来的同门到齐
After the rest of the members are here,
就和你联络，走吧
I'll contact you, go!
从后门走
Leave at the back door.
好
Alright.
我记挂着洪师兄的伤势
I worry about Brother Hong's injuries.
老和尚，这里有一个至善大师吗？
Old monk, is there a Master Zhishan here?
还好你没骂人
Good thing that you weren't rude.
这位就是至善师父了
This is Master Zhishan.
谁说难找，一下就找到了
I didn't expect he'd be so easy to find.
这位小施主找我？
You were looking for me?
要你的老命
To kill you.
老的打不过，打小的
Old one too tough; guess I will see to the younger ones.
高进忠，少林叛逆至善为首
Zhishan is the head of those Shaolin members.
门人之中方世玉最强
His best student is Fang Shiyu.
先除方世玉，再合歼至善
Tackle Fang Shiyu first; then we'll both kill Zhishan.
方世玉自小由他母亲苗翠花
Fang Shiyu's mother Miao Cuihua
用药浸洗全身
soaked him in herbal medicine when he was young.
除了下阴，他是刀剑难伤
It's hard to hurt him with swords except his crotch.
你引他起飞脚，由我下手
Try to make him kick, then I'll take care of it.
至善全身也只有双目和下阴
For Zhishan,
是功夫练不到之处
his weakest parts are his eyes 1and crotch.
你攻他双目，引他注意保护眼睛
Attack his eyes, so that he'll try to protect them.
我来取他下阴
Then I'll attack his crotch.
好
Sure
上
Go!
至善已死
Zhishan's dead.
少林弟子之中只剩下洪举官一人
Hong Xiguan is the only Shaolin member left.
也被我打成重伤，不足为患
He's not a threat, I injured him well.
高进忠，你带着他们四个人
Gao Jinzhong, you take the four of them,
追寻洪举官
and try to locate Hong Xiguan.
一找到就地格杀
Kill him once you've found him.
是
Yes.
洪师哥
Brother Hong.
王师弟，你一个人在这儿？
Brother Wang, you're here alone?
离开少林寺之后大家都走散了
I got parted from others after we left Shaolin Temple.
我还在找至善师父和师兄弟们
I'm still trying to look for Master Zhishan & the rest.
许多师兄弟都在西禅寺殉难了
Many of them died in West Meditation Temple.
至善师父和方师弟他们还在庆云寺
Zhishan and Brother Fang are still in Qingyun Temple.
我就是刚刚从那边来的
I came from there.
现在洪师哥打算去哪儿？
Where do you plan to go now?
你受了伤？
Are you hurt?
是，师父命我同红船上的韩七联络
Yes, the master sent me to contact Han Qi.
不过我离开庆云寺
But when I left Qingyun Temple,
和星龙长老分手之后
and bid goodbye to Master Xinglong
并给高进忠一帮人给追上了
Gao Jinzhong and his gang caught up with me.
还不知道会不会追到这儿来
I'm not sure whether they'll find me here.
那你还是快走吧
Then you had better leave.
要是高进忠他们追到这里
If they get here,
我会相机行事
I'll deal with them.
也好，我们两个在一块儿
At least we're here together,
反而会都脱不了身的
we'll think of something.
我先走
I'm heading off.
你直接去找韩七联络就行了
Try to find Han Qi.
是，师哥，你身上有伤要小心
Yes. Please be careful with your wounds.
我知道，你也要小心，我走了
I know. You be careful too. I'm off.
洪举官
Hong Xiguan.
你们这两个家伙
You two!
来呀
Come on!
再来一次
Another round!
一指定中原
Power of a finger.
下来这儿
Get down here.
你就是洪举官？
You're Hong Xiguan?
是
Yes.
令师星龙长老命我来见周师傅
Your master Xinglong sent me here to meet Master Zhou.
请周师傅替我疗伤
I hope that you could treat me.
本来武林一脉
We're both in the martial arts world,
你受了重伤又曾见过我师父
you're badly injured and have met my master.
可惜我这间武馆地方浅窄
Yet my school is just a small place;
实在容纳不了你老哥这样的
It has no room for such
大英雄、大豪杰
a big hero like yourself.
周师傅，不用说了
Master Zhou, say no more.
我非常明白你的意思，就此告辞
I understand. Goodbye.
洪英雄
Hero Hong.
干什么？
What are you doing?
对不起，客倌
Sorry, sir.
快起来…起来
Get up!
杨大宝，你搞什么鬼？
Yang Dabao, what's wrong with you?
我搞什么鬼？
What's wrong with me?
你看看这些凳子
Look at these stools!
凳子？登子是好的，你看
They're all in good condition, look!
好的？
Good condition?
我坐着就没事
I don't have any problem with it.
老板你看，凳子是好的
Look! All in one piece.
他们不会坐
They just don't know how to sit properly.
客倌，里面请，请
Welcome!
请坐，坐
Please have a seat.
该怎么坐？用四平大马还是子午马
So, how should I sit?
客倌您说笑了，怎么坐都行
Sir, you're kidding. You can sit whatever way you want.
快点，对不起，快点拿张凳子来
Hurry! Sorry. Take a stool
送到那边去
and put it over there.
来了
Coming.
客倌你…
You...
走开
Beat it.
你是黑虎门的？
Black Tiger Clan?
我要找一个人叫韩七
I'm looking for a person named Han Qi,
是在红船上做小武的
he works as an acrobat in the theatre troupe.
你认识不认识
Have you heard of him?
就是韩七，我看过他演戏
Han Qi! I've watched him perform.
红船这两天会来
His red boat will arrive in a few days.
客倌你好像受了伤
You seem to be injured.
算我多嘴
Sorry, it's none of my business.
偷懒扣工钱，打烂了东西扣工钱
I'll deduct from your pay if you slack off,
铺子开迟了也得要扣工钱
break anything or open late.
见鬼，得请和尚道士来念念经才行
Damn! I must find a monk for a ceremony.
老兄，你撞翻了我的东西了
Hey, pal! You knocked off my stuff.
怎么搞的，这么大人走路还翻跟头
What's the matter? Can't you walk properly?
真是，我看你八成喝醉酒了
I think you're drunk.
真麻烦
Such trouble!
你是什么人？
Who are you?
陈阿金…
Chen Ajin.
杨大宝，快来
Yang Dabao, come on in.
你让我给你推磨？我可不干
You want me to do yourjob? Never.
跟我的功夫不是一路
It's different from my martial arts style.
你看看
Look.
他是什么人？怎么会在这儿？
Who is he? What's he doing here?
你认识他？
You know him?
不认识，白天在店里见过
No. I saw him in the restaurant earlier.
他是什么人？
Who is he?
我也不知道
Not too sure myself.
在他身上找到了一张纸，你看看
I found this piece of paper on him. Read it.
你也不把灯点起来
Light up!
这么黑你让我怎么看
I can't read anything in the dark.
上面说些什么？
What does it say?
你也不识字
You are an illiterate too?
我看这个人有点来头
I think he must be an important person.
老板回来了
The boss is back.
这是本门师祖星龙长老
This prescription was written by my master's
开的一张疗伤药方
master, Xinglong.
这人伤得很重
He's badly injured.
伤者在里边
The injured person is inside.
他是洪举官
He's Hong Xiguan.
什么？
What?
他是洪举官
He's Hong Xiguan
就是朝廷下令捉拿的大英雄洪举官
The one who's wanted by the Court?
想不到我们能有机会
I never expected that we'd have a chance
和名满天下的大豪杰在一块儿
to meet such a hero.
他的情形很坏
Looks like he's in a pretty bad state.
我去抓药
I'll get the medicine.
师祖开的药方子一定对症
The old master's prescription would work.
绝不能让人知道
Don't let anyone find out though.
能为洪举官砍头也不枉此一生
I wouldn't mind sacrificing for Hong Xiguan.
这样砍了头也好过一世磨豆腐
I'd rather be beheaded than to make tofu my whole life.
"Yan Shou Herbal shop"
多少钱？
How much is it?
每副是三两四钱五分银子
Three taels forty five cents each.
两副就是…
Times two, that comes to...
什么？一副药要那么贵
What? It's so expensive.
这副药可不是普通药
This isn't an ordinary prescription.
单是熊胆末、犀角粉
It costs two taels eighty cents for
这两样已经是二两八钱了
just the bear's bladder and rhino's horn powder.
你干什么？
What are you doing?
药先存着，我没带够钱回去拿
Keep it for me, I don't have enough cash, I'll be back.
我只有一两多银子还不够，你们…
I only have one tael, what about you?
你不是有银子藏着要来娶老婆的
Don't you have some money for your future wedding?
只不过二两，我存了两年了
Only two taels, I saved up for two years.
拿出来…救人要紧
Take it out... for saving a life.
拿出来？
What?
拿出来，救人要紧
Saving a life is more important.
拿来吧，快去
Come on.
还不够啊
Still not enough.
你还有银子存在衣服里
I think you have some money.
快点，快拿出来
Hurry up! Take it out!
快一点，快拿出来
Come on!
你昨天晚上吃了一副药睡得好沉
You slept well after you took the medicine last night.
今天精神好点了吧
Are you feeling better?
三位，我与你们素不相识，你们…
I'm a complete stranger to you, yet you three...
洪大侠别放在心上
You're very welcome, Master Hong.
我们虽然是小人物
Although we are nobody,
可是也知道你是英雄豪杰
but we know that you're a hero.
应该尽力的来帮你
That's why we'd like to help.
像你们那样才是真正的英雄豪杰
You're indeed the real heroes.
快
Come on.
这个药很灵，可是还要多喝几服
This is good medicine, I guess you'd need to continue.
对，至少再喝十副八副
Yes, at least ten times.
买药的钱呢？
What about the money for the medicine?
怎么我问你们不出声啊？
Why don't you answer?
我连老婆本都挖出来了
I even used up the savings for my wedding.
平时你办法最多，该你想办法
You're the one with all the ideas, think of a plan!
好，我们来想想办法
Alright, let us think!
偷
Steal!
媚姑，今天这么早
You're early today, Mei.
阿金，来两块这样的豆腐
Jin, two pieces of tofu.
今天的豆腐包你新鲜
They're really fresh today.
这豆腐真不错，挺新鲜
Yes, looks like it.
阿金，给我包两块豆腐
Give me two pieces, Jin.
谢谢
Thanks.
回家吧
Let's go.
朱财，今天你怎么了？
Zhu Cai, what's the matter with you?
没什么，大叔
Nothing.
穷人急着要钱有什么办法
What can the poor do to get cash quick?
有，有一招，是穷人派的绝招
Yes, there's one thing.
这一招…
It's called...
这一招叫做举世均图
Pawn things.
伙计，算账
The bill please.
一共是一钱二分
Twelve cents.
一钱二分
客倌，我叫的菜不错吧？
Did you enjoy the meal?
还算过得去，我们走吧
It's alright, let's go.
可能吃得太饱了
Think I'm too full.
是，两位慢走
Good day.
拿去，谢谢
Take it. Thanks.
来买豆腐？今天的豆腐很新鲜
Tofu? It's fresh today!
最大块的，拿去
The biggest piece, here you go.
王嫂，好久不见你，买豆腐？
Mrs. Wang, it's been a while. Want some tofu?
今天豆腐好新鲜
Very fresh today.
包你新鲜，常来光顾
Please come back again.
阿金，你做什么？
Jin, what are you doing?
没什么，好痒
Nothing, it tickles.
我买豆腐…
Tofu...
有人买豆腐
A customer!
新鲜的豆腐，刚刚磨出来的
Fresh tofu!
你买回去包你满意
The best quality!
拿回去，下次记着再来买，谢谢
Here you go! Come back again! Thanks!
看不出你平时是木头木脑的
Who would have thought?
偷起钱来是又凶又狠
A dumb wit like you would steal from me!
你数数看一共偷了我多少钱
Count it! You've stolen so much from me!
你想叫我血本无归啊
I'm running a business here.
我平时对你不错，供你吃供你住
I've been treating you well.
你这个畜牲
You bastard!
你偷我一文钱我就扣你十文工钱
You must pay ten times of what you've stolen from me.
臭小子你服不服？
Do you understand?
"Pawn"
陈阿金，你那里有多少钱？
Chen Ajin, how much do you have?
我这里有…
I've got...
你是来找陈阿金的？
You're looking for Jin?
你知道不知道阿金偷了我的钱
Do you know that he stole from me?
被我当场抓住了
And I caught him!
我看你鬼头鬼脑的也不是好东西
You don't look like a decent person too.
你来干什么？
What are you here for?
我…
I...
你来干什么的？
What are you doing here?
我来买豆腐的
I'm here to buy tofu.
买豆腐？买多少？
Buy tofu? How much?
全买了
All of it.
大主顾来了，慢慢再跟你算账
We've a big spender today! I'll deal with you later.
来
Come on.
你买这么多的豆腐不好拿
It won't be easy for you to carry with all that tofu,
我叫伙计替你送去
I'll get my staff to help.
好好替他送去，快去快回
Make the delivery and come back soon.
你要是偷懒我就扣你的工钱
I'll deduct from your pay if you try to slack off.
就是你
It's you!
这些花瓶很名贵的
Do you know how expensive the vase is?
你也是的，买这么多豆腐怎么办
What did you buy all that tofu for?
是你叫我买的，你没弄到钱
You told me so. You didn't get any money.
我把什么都送到当铺去
I pawned everything,
换了二十板豆腐回来
and now I've all this tofu.
你们两个在搞什么鬼？
What on earth are you two doing?
你去买药去，把豆腐交给我
Go get the medicine, hand me the tofu.
杨大宝，你上哪儿去了？
Yang Dabao, where are you off to?
哎，你干什么？
What are you doing?
老板，有大生意上门了
Boss, we've got big business.
有贵客要吃各种豆腐
We have guests who like tofu.
贵客？在哪儿？
Guests? Where?
贵客来了，你先把豆腐端到厨房去
If they are, bring these to the kitchen first.
我去招呼
I'll take care of them.
坐…
Please sit down.
有什么吃的？
What's on the menu?
有，豆腐
Oh, tofu.
先来两斤牛肉
How about some beef first?
牛肉都是上个月没有卖完的
The beef, we kept it from last month.
又酸又臭，豆腐最新鲜
It's gone bad! Tofu is fresh.
光吃豆腐怎么行啊
But we can't just eat tofu.
小店专卖豆腐，花样可多了
Tofu is our specialty.
有煎豆腐、炸豆腐、清蒸豆腐
We've fried, deep-fried, steamed,
红烧豆腐、鸡肠豆腐、八珍豆腐
stewed, diced, chilled,
麻婆豆腐、砂锅豆腐、炖豆腐
with vegetables, with minced pork,
香豆腐、麻油拌豆腐、韭菜炒豆腐
in a soup... you name it, we have it.
将这豆腐每一样炒一大碟
All of the above!
各位就来…
Coming right up...
现在的时势
At this time...
哪有平常百姓带着家伙满街跑
No one would carry weapons so openly,
一定是官府当差的
must be some kind of officers.
谢谢
Thanks.
老板
Boss.
曾大少
Master Zeng.
刚才那人来买什么药？
What did he buy just now?
上好的伤药，买了很多次了
The best, he's been here a few times.
照我看起来
I think someone is badly injured.
好像是有人受了很重的内伤
Internal injuries.
你可记得方子
Can you remember the prescription?
周师傅，这位高大人是我的朋友
Master Zhou, this is my friend Official Gao.
他奉令缉拿叛贼洪举官
He's on the Court's order to catch Hong Xiguan.
还要请周师傅多多帮忙
Please assist him anyway you can.
一定一定
Certainly.
我们要追寻的叛贼洪举官
We're trying to look for Hong Xiguan.
据白眉师父说他受的是内伤
According to my master White Brows, Hong's injuries
只有喇嘛派才会治
can only be healed by the Lama Clan.
洪举官不会来找周师傅治伤吧
I wonder if Hong Xiguan came to you for help.
不瞒高提督，洪举官是来找过我
To be frank, he did.
我是守法良民
I'm a law-abiding citizen.
这种叛贼找上门来
A traitor like him came for help,
我当然把他赶走了
I kicked him out right away.
周师傅，要是当时你将他拿下
If Master Zhou captured him on the spot,
倒是替朝廷立了一件大功
you would have helped the court a big deal.
师哥，我看周师傅当时不敢动手
I think master Zhou didn't dare to kill him.
洪举官名头大啊
Hong Xiguan has a reputation.
师傅，有一副方子可是治内伤的
There's one prescription to treat internal injuries.
药方有熊胆末、犀角粉、槲若
Bear's bladder powder, rhino's horn powder...
是，这是本派的秘方
Yes, that's our special prescription.
朱财在买这副药
Zhu Cai bought this prescription many times.
已经买了很多副了，会不会…
Could it be...
对，洪举官来的时候
Right. He's cleaning the room
他正在打扫房间
when Hong Xiguan came here.
谁是朱财？
Who's Zhu Cai?
提督请放心，走不了他
Don't worry, I can take care of him.
他每天会到武馆来
He drops by everyday.
有了叛贼的下落，来，干杯
Cheers! We've found the traitor!
气贯上下，力透全身
Let the "Qi" energy travel through your body.
你们三个人各有所长
You three excel in different areas.
不过没有人指点你们运气的法门
But no one has taught you about the Qi.
出招之际难免有力不从心之感
That's why you might find it difficult
难达上乘的武功境界
for some complicated martial arts styles.
你们武功已有根底
With your foundation,
可以一点即明
it's easy for you to learn.
我教你们少林正宗的运气之法门
Let me teach you Shaolin's own use of "Qi".
气先纳于丹田
Gather "Qi" at diaphragm.
我们家招待贵客，厨子不够用
We're treating a VIP guest & we don't have enough chefs
要用你们酒馆里的厨子是看得起你
It's a compliment that we're using your chef.
这个没有厨子我们怎么做生意
How can I run a restaurant without a chef?
你知道我家的贵客什么身份
Do you have any idea who my guest is?
谁理你做不做生意
Who cares whether or not you can do business!
进去把厨子拉出来
Get the chef!
慢着…老兄…有话慢慢说
Wait...
像我们这种小馆子
We're just a small restaurant,
厨子的手艺也好不到哪儿去
our chef isn't that good.
对，煮出来的菜只配喂猪
Yes, the dishes are only good for pigs.
是，这位客倌说的对
Well said.
你要招待贵宾
For your VIP guest,
如果是猪那我们的厨子就有用了
our chef is only useful if you're serving a pig.
你胡言乱语什么？
What are you on about?
别打…别打了
Stop!
老板，不打不行
Boss, we must.
厨子给他们拉起来
They've got the chef;
咱们就没有生意做了
without him, we've no business.
打…
Beat him!
打
来…
Come on!
快走…
Run!
我自己会走
I can walk myself out.
一、二、三
One, two, three.
打…店里的东西全给你们打烂了
You broke everything!
我要扣你们工钱
I'll deduct from your pay
干什么？
What are you doing?
一、二、三
One, two, three.
我叫韩七
I'm Han Qi.
我看过你做戏
I've seen you act.
洪举官大哥在找你
Brother Hong Xiguan is looking for you.
我也在找他
I'm looking for him too.
白天人杂，晚上你来找我
Come pick me up tonight,
咱们一块儿去见他
we'll go meet him.
好
Sure.
师傅
Master.
朱财，你到药铺去买伤药
Zhu Cai, the medicine you bought,
给什么人治伤的？
who's that for?
说，给谁治伤？
Speak up! Who's that for?
给我自己的，我这里疼
For myself, it hurts here.
怕是练功练坏了，给我自己服的
Must be from the practising. It's for myself.
你这里疼？
Hurts here?
是
Yes.
你倒有先见之明知道自己胸口会疼
Interesting that you can foresee your own injuries.
快说，给谁治伤的？
Speak up! Who's that for?
是给我自己
For myself.
除了胸口你还有什么地方疼？
Where else does it hurt?
这里疼，不…哪儿也不疼了
Here... no... nowhere.
那你买药干什么？
What's the medicine for?
洪举官才要这种汤药的
Only Hong Xiguan would need a prescription like that.
朱财，带提督大人去找洪举官
Zhu Cai, if you show Official Gao to Hong Xiguan,
是大功一件
that's a merit.
洪举官在哪里？快说
Speak up! Where is Hong Xiguan?
我看他鬼头鬼脑在豆腐店里进出
He sneaks around in the tofu shop,
说不定洪举官就藏在豆腐店里
I think Hong Xiguan could be there.
不，洪举官不在豆腐店…
No! He's not!
小子，你不打自招了
Alright! You did us a favour.
你是什么人？
Who are you?
放开我，我是老板
Let me go! I'm the boss.
陈阿金，快溜
Chen Ajin, run!
站住
Freeze.
洪举官在哪里？快说
Where's Hong Xiguan? Speak up.
在你姥姥家里
At your grandma's.
你，这怎么行？
You! You can't do that
这还差不多
This is more likely.
我们来放火趁乱救人
Set a fire! And we can save them.
他们两个在下面，我们在放火
They're below. We're setting a fire.
快走…
Run!
别乱，走，追
Don't panic! Run! Go!
快走啊…
Run!
往那边跑了，快追啊
Over there! Go!
追
Go!
到哪儿去？
Where to?
染房就在这儿，我们进去躲一躲
The dye factory is right here, let's hide inside.
不行，官兵一到
No, when they arrive,
一定会料到我们躲到染房去
they would know that we're hiding there.
我们到周成的武馆去躲一躲
We should hide in Zhou Cheng's martial arts school.
好主意，走
Good idea!
来了，恭喜提督抓住了洪举官
Here you are! Congratulations on catching Hong Xiguan,
替朝廷立了大功
what an achievement!
我来倒是来了
Well, I'm here.
不过不是叫人抓来的
But no one caught me.
你别去，免得到时候你为难
You stay here. It's better for you.
好酒好菜
What a meal!
别糟蹋了好酒好菜
Let's not ruin it.
是啊
That's right.
朱财在染房工作
Zhu Cai works in the dye factory,
他一定藏在染房里头
he must be hiding in there.
他们在武馆，师傅…
They're in the school, the master...
小心点，你带头
Careful. After you!
我？
Me?
快去
Go!
原来早走了
They're gone.
喂，放心进来，没有人
Hey! Come on in! No one's here.
我进去看看你们跟我来
I'll take a look first, follow me.
这小子怎么忽然胆子大起来了？
How come he's suddenly acting so brave?
人都走了，胆子还不大？
They're gone, of course he would.
里边没有人
It's clear.
那面就是染房，不知道他们在不在
Next door is the dye factory, wonder if they're there.
灯火都没有，大概都逃了
No lights. Guess they must have fled.
提督大人，我遇事勇敢向前
Official Gao, I'm being brave,
该记一功吧
I deserve a credit.
好，记你一功
Sure, you do.
他们在墙那边
They're over there at the wall.
他们在暗，我们在明
They're in the dark.
天黑地形不熟，攻过去会吃亏的
Unfamiliarity with the settings is to our disadvantage.
曾世光就是榜样
Zeng Shiguang is an example.
快去衙门调动人马
Go to the magistrate's office and get some manpower.
把所有出路封死
Block all the exits.
是
Yes.
兵还是要调
We indeed need the manpower.
不过现在深更半夜我怕打草惊蛇
But it's late in the night, I'd rather not alert them.
一来没跟官府联络
And besides, we haven't contacted the magistrate,
只怕不到天亮人马不易调集
I worry that we can't get any help until daybreak.
暂时只好虚张声势
All we can do is bluff for now,
等天亮再调集兵马
we'll get the men in the morning.
他们怎么还不攻过来？
Why don't they attack?
我们熄灭了灯火
There's no light.
黑夜之间他们地形不熟不敢攻过来
They wouldn't dare to attack in the dark.
弓箭手守左边见人就射
The archers on the left, shoot when you spot anyone.
刀斧手守右边见人就砍
Soldiers with axes on the right, chop if you see anyone
我们一夜不断骚扰他们
We'll keep disturbing them over the night.
令他们不能睡，也不敢逃
That way, they can't sleep and dare not escape.
等天明再攻
We'll launch a proper attack tomorrow.
我看都是虚张声势
I think it's just a bluff,
不过还是要做好准备
but we need to be prepared.
掌力有阴力阳力之分
The power of the palm is different between yin & yang.
运气得当掌力阴阳自若
After controlling your "Qi" right, you can master it.
阿金，你来试试
Ah Jin, you try.
你气集的还不够，再来
You're not focused enough... once again.
这样就差不多了
That's better.
不错
Not bad.
反贼听着，官兵已经团团围住
Listen up, traitors! You've been surrounded.
这里就是你们葬身之地了
This is where you'll die.
阿金，不行
Ah Jin, no!
周成这桌酒席让我全搬来了
I brought Zhou Cheng's feast here.
大家开怀畅饮吧
Let's have a good meal!
对呀，反正一有人过来
That's right. If someone comes close,
那个板会有声音的
we can hear.
我把兵器架都搬过来了
I'll move all the weapons here.
我看不如把兵器先藏起来
I think we should hide them first.
来，坐
Come on.
别看刚才我们脱身容易
Let's not congratulate ourselves for escaping earlier;
那是高进忠他们一时轻敌
It's only because Gao Jinzhong's gang underestimated us
这五个人的武功非同寻常
Those five are very skilled,
后面还有官府的力量
and they're backed by the court.
事情本来和你们一点关系也没有的
You had nothing to do with it,
你们替我治伤我已经感激不尽了
I appreciate that you helped me with my medicine.
三位如果要走的话我绝不见怪
I wouldn't blame you for wanting to leave now.
反正他们的目标也只在我一人身上
I'm their target.
洪举官原来你心里还看不起我们
Hong Xiguan, you despise us.
我洪举官要是对三位有轻视之意
If I meant anything like that,
就天打雷劈
please let me be struck by thunder.
刚才是我说错话了，三位不要见怪
I was wrong, please forgive me.
来，坐
Come on, sit.
能认识三位这样的好朋友
I'm honoured to have friends like you.
真是生平的快事
This is certainly something to celebrate for.
长夜漫漫
It's a long night.
不如我们一边喝酒一边谈论武功
Let's drink and talk about martial arts.
来
Come!
请洪大哥指教
Brother Hong, please teach us.
白眉道人的武功是出于武当
Earlier on, Priest White Brows learnt from Wudang Clan;
高进忠是他的首徒
Gao Jinzhong remains his best student.
听说他师徒二人有意自创白眉一派
I hear they're hoping to build up a White Brows Clan.
我们第一个要当心的人就是高进忠
We must watch out for Gao Jinzhong first,
特别是要留心他的辫子
especially his braid.
所谓知己知彼
Know your enemy!
还有邹风的盾单刀，阴森快捷
Zou Feng's sword strikes fast and sneaky.
他以盾牌护身不易攻得进去
He has a shield to protect himself.
还要留心他的单刀穿盾而出
Watch out for his sword breaking through the shield,
防不胜防
that's his trick.
范天聪力大无穷
Fan Tiancong is a man with massive strength.
现在打墙的想必是他
I think he's the one hitting the wall now.
他每一锤有三百斤力道以上
Each strike is deadly,
绝不可以与他硬碰硬
we must think of a way to deal with him.
闷死了，过去看看怎么样
So boring! Let's check them!
好
Sure.
好，你接应我
You cover for me.
走
Go!
这就是白眉双童的虎童和豹童
They are the Tiger Kid and Leopard Kid.
虎童拳脚功夫很辣，劲力极足
Tiger Kid has a deadly kick.
豹童的金钢圈武艺非凡
Leopard Kid kills with the copper ring.
尤其是别看他们是小孩子
Don't think that they're just kids,
出手阴毒，千万小心
they're very vicious. You must be careful.
官兵已在聚集，很快就可以赶到了
The soldiers are gathering, they'll be here soon.
慢着，来呀
Wait. Come on.
来
Come on.
喝一杯
Have a drink.
这叫什么功夫？
What style is this?
这叫黑虎门功夫
The Black Tiger Clan's style.
朱财…
Zhu Cai...
大宝…
Dabao...
洪大哥，官兵到了
Brother Hong, the soldiers are here!
你和韩七走，我来挡住
Leave with Han Qi, I'll stay behind.
不行
No!
反正我已经受了伤
I'm injured anyway.
快点走，再不走就来不及了
Leave now! Or you won't make it!
我们在这儿挡着
We'll stay behind and block them.
阿金伤得也很厉害
Jin's badly injured too.
大家都要留下来送死，谁来干大事
If we all die, who's going to complete the mission?
快点走啊
Run!
走
放箭
Shoot!
大宝，人生一世算没白活
Dabao, we lived life to the fullest.
很过瘾.是不是？
Fun, isn't it?